all right so why should you listen to
some random dude in a white T-shirt
standing in front of a whiteboard my
name is Matt I'm a current strategy
associate at Google prior to that was a
consultant at BCG and today I'm going to
walk you through a McKenzie style case
and how I would solve it now keep in
mind that there are multiple ways to get
to the right solution in a case and so
what I'm going to show you today is just
my Approach feel free to take a
different approach if you think that is
more appropriate but the reason why I'm
making this video today is because I've
made similar case walkthroughs in the
past and have received really good
feedback and so today we're going to do
a McKenzie style case interview and I'm
going to walk you through my thought
process so that you can understand a
little bit better what to expect from a
case interview and what the typical flow
of a case should sound like hope this
helps let's get right into it all right
so the case we're going to do today is
about a company called superp soda so
our client is super soda a top three
beverage producer in the United States
that has approached McKenzie for help
designing its product launch strategy so
as an integrated Beverage Company super
leads its own brand design marketing and
sales efforts the company also owns its
entire beverage supply chain including
production of concentrates bottling and
packaging and distribution to retail
outlets superp soda has a considerable
number of Brands across carbonated and
non-carbonated drinks five large
bottling plants throughout the country
and distribution agreements with most
major retailers super soda is a
valuating the launch of a new product a
flavored sports drink called electrolyte
sports drinks are usually designed to
replenish energy with sugar and
electrolytes or salts in the body
however electrolyte has been formulated
to focus more on the replenishment of
electrolytes and has a lower sugar
content compared to most other sports
drings the company expects this new
beverage to capitalize on the recent
Trend away from high sugar products vice
president of marketing has asked
McKenzie to help analyze key factors
surrounding the launch of electrolyte
and its own internal capabilities to
support that effort okay so the first
question is what key factors should
super soda consider when deciding
whether or not to launch electrolyte all
right so the first thing that we always
want to do when we are given a case
prompt is we want to obviously take
quick notes while the interviewer is
giving you the prompt and so I'm just
going to write down really quickly some
Keynotes that I heard during the initial
readout of the prompt okay so basically
what I've done here is I have written
down a quick summary of what I heard so
I wrote that super soda is a beverage
producer they are evaluating the launch
of a new drink called electrolyte and
the overarching question here is what
should they consider when thinking about
whether or not to launch this new
product and I've also noted here that
electrolyte has a lower sugar content
than most other sports drinks in the
market okay so don't overthink this part
just take quick notes and immediately
after you take notes you want to
basically restate to the interviewer
what you heard to make sure that you
understand it fully and also ask a few
clarifying questions now the reason why
you want to ask clarifying questions is
not only to make sure that you
understand the prompt correctly and to
dig maybe a little bit deeper but also
because you really need to demonstrate
to the interviewer that you are
listening and thinking thoughtfully
about the prompt and the company and so
even if you don't really have any major
questions I highly recommend that you
still come up with at least one or two
questions that you can ask the
interviewer before you start thinking
about your framework okay so I've just
put together three quick clarifying
questions now I want to caveat that you
do not need to ask the questions that
I've come up with you can come up with
different ones these are just the ones
that came to mind for me and I'll just
walk you through each so the first one
is have they tried anything already this
basically just means has the company
done any research or has management
tried anything to test whether or not
launching this new product into the
market would be a success or not and
this is just really to see if they have
any sort of like pre-existing
information that could potentially help
you out in the case now often times
you're interviewer is probably just
going to say no they haven't done
anything and which is why they've hired
you but it's just a good question to ask
that I view as really no regrets the
second question that I've put together
is What markets are they targeting and
so this is a good question to ask
because whenever we're thinking about
launching a new product one of the
biggest questions is where are we going
to launch it right is it going to be
localized to the east coast in the US or
is it going to be across the entire
nation is it going to be in multiple
countries are we going to be focused on
North America America only or are we
also going to go into APAC and emia
thinking about these things is really
important which is why I've asked here
if they're targeting any specific
markets because depending on what Market
that they want to launch the new product
in this is going to dictate their
strategy now the third question that
I've also mentioned is have any
competitors launched similar products
now I know that the initial prompt said
that this new product was supposed to be
differentiated based on the fact that it
had lower sugar content but a question
that I still have is has anyone already
launched a similar low sugar energy
drink into the market it's very possible
that one of their competitors could have
already beat them to the punch and so
you know this might not mean that they
shouldn't launch the product but it
would mean that we would have to be
thoughtful about how we position our
product against the competitor's
existing product but anyways after you
come up with your clarifying questions
and you ask the interviewer the next
thing you're going to do is you are
going to start building your framework
and so what is a framework well I know a
lot of you probably already know but if
you don't a framework is just a set of
key buckets that you as the interviewer
would like to investigate and learn a
little bit more in order to get to the
root cause of the problem or in this
case learning a little bit more about
what might inform our product launch
strategy and so some general rules of
thumb with Frameworks is you want to
make them as Mei as possible which means
mutually exclusive and collectively
exhaustive simply meaning that the
buckets the topics in your framework
should not have any kind of overlap if
possible and also they should Encompass
the entire universe of possibilities
because the last thing you want is to
miss out on a option that just simply
wasn't included in your framework but
potentially could be the key to the case
and so the way you want to go about
creating your framework is you want to
tell the interviewer okay great can I
take 30 seconds or a minute to just
structure my thoughts and they will
always say yes and this is your cue to
kind of go ahead and start building out
a framework now in practice how do you
do this well the typical way that you
want to build a framework is you want to
make a list with multiple buckets as I
mentioned and so for example even
something as simple as this 1 2 3 could
function as a framework now obviously
you're going to need to put some thought
into what goes into each of these rows
but at the core this in and of itself
could be a framework I would highly
recommend that you have at least three
buckets when coming up with the
framework but no more than five because
less than three is a little bit too
simplistic sometimes and greater than
five can be a little bit too much and so
I'm just going to go ahead and put
together a quick framework here okay so
I've put together a quick framework
right here and see if you can even see
that basically what I've taken here is
what's known as the business situation
framework it's a very common framework
but it works very well with a lot of
Consulting cases and to walk you through
each of the buckets the way that I would
present this to an interviewer is I
would say okay great so there are
broadly speaking four buckets that I
would want to consider when thinking
about the product launch strategy for
this business for this new product the
first is going to be the customer the
second is going to be the competition
the third is going to be the company
itself and the fourth is going to be the
product and I'll now talk a little bit
about each of these buckets so going
back to my first bucket which is the
customer here I would be most interested
in one the customer segmentation
otherwise known as you know the
different customer groups that we are
going to be going after for example are
we going after wealthy individuals with
a lot of income that would be interested
in this kind of product or are we going
after the lower income consumer and
second customer preferences what does
our Target customer value and what do
they care about because this is going to
inform how we actually think about
launching the product second competition
talking a little bit here there's two
things that I'm most interested in the
first is the market for these kinds of
quote unquote healthy low sugar energy
drinks is it a large Market is it a
small Market if it's a large market then
maybe it's a good idea to enter this
Market if it's small maybe not so much
we can't really make this decision in
isolation but it will inform our
ultimate recommendation and kind of tied
to that is the growth of the market is
this Market growing or is it shrinking
if it is a small Market but it is
growing then that is a good sign but
conversely if it is a large Market but
shrinking then maybe we need to be a
little bit more careful about this and
secondly under competition who are the
competitors that currently play I'm sure
there are other beverage companies out
there who have tried something similar
or are currently competing with us in
the energy drink Market who are they how
many of them are there how big are they
is this a market with a lot of small
players AKA a fragmented Market or is it
a market with a few key players that
dominate the space which would make it
quite difficult for a new entrant to
come in now thirdly the company I'm
interested in two things what do our
supply chain capabilities look like and
two what about our sales and marketing
capabilities and specifically when I
talk about supply chain I'm talking
about the strength of our supply chain
because if we have a very strong supply
chain this will make it easier for us to
launch a new product now it sounds like
we do have a very strong supply chain
given the information at the beginning
of the case that was given to us right
they own end to-end the distribution and
Bing which gives them a lot of control
they also have five very large bottling
plants that is a very good sign for us
because then we don't have to depend on
thirdparty providers or other partners
basically to help us with launching this
new product and then with sales and
marketing here I want to just better
understand hey how strong is our sales
and marketing team and do they have
experience in the past with launching a
new product in this manner finally
moving to the product there's three
buckets here that I've put down the
first is what is our cost to produce
this new new product second is what are
we pricing it at because again very
important to consider because our
pricing is going to ultimately also
influence our product positioning which
is the third bucket and the product
positioning is a fancy word for
basically when a consumer sees our
product on the shelves what do we want
them to think what associations do we
want people to have with our new product
you know when you see a bottle of coke
at Walmart what sort of associations do
you get from that in that same way we
also really want to care about our
product positioning because especially
if this is a new market it the
positioning is going to heavily dictate
the reaction that we get and also
whether or not we end up targeting the
right people right so this is the
framework that I've put together I want
to caveat that this is not the only
thing that could work this is just a
easy framework for people to use that
works with probably 90% of business
strategy cases and so that's why I use
it to teach but in reality you could
technically come up with an unlimited
number of Frameworks that could
hypothetically work for this kind of a
question but basically you want to
present the framework to your
interviewer and walk them through those
buckets as I just did to you and from
there there's two things that could
happen one is the interviewer could
point you towards a certain bucket which
is what's known as interviewer-led cases
where the interviewer is sort of guiding
you towards the right approach or if
you're doing an interview Le case they
might ask you okay so which bucket do
you think is most interesting and that
you want to look into first and then the
onus is on you to then identify the
bucket in your framework that you think
is most relevant and ask some more
questions related to that but in this
case because this is a McKenzie style
case McKenzie cases are usually
interviewer Le and so the interviewer is
basically going to lead us to the second
question which is after reviewing the
factors that super soda should consider
when deciding whether to launch
electrolyte your team wants to
understand the beverage market and
consumer preferences to gauge the
potential success of your team has
gathered the following information about
the US sports drink Market the
information shows an estimated share of
electrolyte drinks as well as the
current share for the two main
electrolyte products Cool sweat and
recover plus okay so now they're going
to give us an exhibit basically showing
us the share of the US Sports string
market and so a quick rule of thumb is
that whenever you are given any kind of
exhibit in a case interview the first
thing that your brain is often going to
want to do is you're going to start
wanting to think about like things that
you should say
right you know you want to sound smart
or something and so you want to tell the
interviewer some insight that you just
thought of but before you do that I
implore you my recommendation is that
you should actually first just talk
aloud and describe what you are seeing
to the interviewer and so the way I
would go about this is I would say okay
so this is really interesting so it
looks like we've been given some
information related to the total market
for us sports drinks which is about 8
billion gallons and we've also been
given some detail about the electrolyte
drinks Market which is only about 5% of
the total us sports drink market and I
can see here that there's a few key
competitors in the electrolyte drinks
Market Cool sweat and recover plus that
we might need to watch out for and so
the reason why I recommend just
restating what you see is because this
often buys you time and allows you to
sort of process the information a little
bit easier and I've often found that by
speaking aloud my brain just understands
what I'm seeing a little bit better than
if I were to just silently stare at this
exhibit and then suddenly try to come up
with some key Insight now in this
scenario the interviewer is going to
actually start giving us more
information because there's a Quant
question coming up and they're going to
tell us based on the Target price and
upfront fixed costs what share of the
electrolyte drink Market would
electrolyte need to capture to break
even here is some additional information
for you to consider as you form your
response so electrolyte would launch in
a 16 ooun format or 1/8 of a gallon at a
price of $2 to retailers to be able to
launch electrolyt super soda needs to
Bear $40 million in total fixed costs
including marketing expenses and
increased costs across its production
and distribution Network and finally the
vice president of Ops operations
estimates that each bottle would cost
$1.90 to produce and deliver in the new
process okay so what I'm about going to
do here is just write down what I heard
ideally in a case scenario you should be
like taking notes so that like as
they're saying it you're getting these
numbers down but because I'm for the
purposes of today I'm literally just
writing on a whiteboard I'm I'm going to
go ahead and write some stuff down here
okay so here I've basically just
summarized the information that was
given at the beginning of this problem
which is we have a 16 oz format it's
going to be priced at $2 a bottle and
it's going to cost us $1.90 to produce
and there's also going to be $40 million
in fixed costs associated with this new
product um and then finally we're given
some Market data as well so we can see
the total market for energy drinks is 8
billion gallons and 5% of that is the
electrolyte drinks Market of which 20%
is Cool sweat and 10% is recover plus
now the question we were asked is what
share do we need as electrolyte in order
to break even and so when you hear the
word break even the first thing you
should be thinking of is profit okay and
costs because Break Even basically means
how much do we need to make in order to
recoup our upfront investment and so the
way I would go about this is basically I
would first try to calculate the per
unit profit that we're getting from each
sale of this new drink right so unit
profit is basically what we're selling
it for which is the price of $2 per
bottle minus the cost per bottle which
we were given was $11.90 and so how many
units do we basically need to sell in
order to recoup this $40 million well
the way you should do this is divide
that 40 million by this profit per
bottle so like I'm just going to be
super clear here and say 10 cents per
bottle that's the unit that we're
dealing with here and so number of
bottles to break even equals $40 million
in fixed costs divided by 10 cents per
bottle okay so and now some of you might
be wondering how am I supposed to do
this math in my head well I'll show you
so 40 million is a pretty big and round
number which is good for us um but then
when we divide by 10 cents some of you
might be feeling a little bit
uncomfortable with this math now what we
have to remember is that 0.1 is the same
as 1 over 10 right and if you guys paid
attention in basic division and
multiplication class or in basic math
class then you should know that when you
divide by a fraction you flip it and you
multiply by the denominator and so this
is the same thing as 40 million * 10
which actually gets us to 400 million
now you have to be careful here though
because 400 million what is that is that
dollars or bottles it's bottles because
the dollar signs here cancel out and so
it's actually 40 million bottles that
you need to sell in order to break even
now some of you may have gotten to this
number without having to watch me do it
you might be patting yourself on the
back right now but we're not done yet
the question if you remember was what
share of the electrolyte drink Market do
we need to break even and so I actually
forgot to write this earlier but we were
also given an important detail in the
beginning of this question which is that
okay the bottles are launched in a 16 oz
format otherwise known as as 1/8 of a
gallon now why is this important well we
need to somehow now convert the 400
million bottles into like a volume unit
so what does 400 million bottles mean in
terms of gallons how many gallons is
that and the way that we're going to get
to that is we're going to multiply the
400 million bottles times 1/8 of a
gallon and so 400 million bottles time
1/8 of a gallon is just 50 million
gallons okay and the reason why I wanted
to convert this to gallons is because
the market share data that we have is in
gallons and so we know that the total
market for sports drinks is 8 billion
gallons now 5% of that 8 billion is
electrolytes right and so I'm going to
start squatting and so 8 billion gallons
times 5% is going to equal whatever the
electrolyte drinks Market is now again
some of you might be feeling a little
bit intimidated by this multiplication
here because you're multiplying a
massive number by a percentage now the
easy way to do this is you can easily
take 10% of any number right because you
just literally take one zero off of the
right side you move the decimal place by
one position when you multiply by 10%
and 5% is just half of 10% so first
let's take 10% of 8 billion and then
let's just divide it by two easy right
so 10% of 8 billion is 800 million half
of 800 million is 400 million and so
that's an easy way so now you know that
the entire electrolyte drinks Market is
400 million gallons okay and so let's
take a step back now cuz I've done a lot
of math why did I want to figure out
what this 5% was in gallons well the
question that we're trying to get to is
what share of the electrolyte drinks
Market do we need to break even and we
figured out how many bottles we're going
to produce to break even it's that 50
million gallons worth of drink but the
last thing we need is to divide it by
the total market for electrolyte drinks
which we've now learned is $400 million
so 50 ID 400 is going to be our answer
now 50 divid 400 is the same as 1/8 1/8
is the same as roughly 12.5% I think and
so the answer very small down there is
12.5% we need 12.5% of the electrolyte
drinks Market in order to break even now
I know that this was a absolute ton of
math and if you're feeling a little bit
overwhelmed right now don't worry these
kinds of quantitative questions get much
easier with practice and so the next
thing that you always want to do after
completing the Quant portion of a case
is you want to take a step back absorb
what you've just learned and think about
what this means in the context of the
case and whether or not you think this
is realistic or not so for example I
would say to the interviewer okay so
I've learned now that we need roughly
12.5% of the market in order to break
even now does this number feel
attainable to me well given what we know
about this Market it looks like only
about 30% is dominated by these major
two players 70% is taken up by other
which I would assume would be smaller
players with less than 10% market share
and so given that I would think it would
be reasonable to assume that a competent
new entrant with the right marketing
strategy and the right product
positioning would be able to capture
12.5% of this market now under what time
frame I don't know that would depend but
seeing this 12.5% and seeing that only
30% is taken up by the top two
competitors gives me a lot of comfort
around that okay so you just want to
give your reaction demonstrate some
critical thinking and show that you're
thinking about what the numbers even
mean in the context of the project okay
but now we're going to move to the third
question and so the interviewer would
basically react to whatever you
discussed in the second question and
then push you towards the third question
because this is an interviewer-led case
and so the third question is subota
Executives believe that the company's
position as a top three beverage company
gives it strategic impetus towards
achieving the desired market share
however they ask the team to outline
What would be needed to achieve the
target 12.5% market share of the
electrolytes drink Market what would
super soda need to do to gain the
required market share for electrolyte
following its launch okay so basically
this third part of the case is what's
known as a brainstorming section and
typically in a brainstorming section
you're just trying to come up with as
many ideas as possible to the question
which in this case is what would they
need to do in order to actually get that
12.5% market share and so it's also okay
here to ask for just 30 seconds if you
don't have have any ideas in mind but if
you do have a few ideas already in mind
feel free to just go ahead and start
listing out ideas to your interviewer
because this this part of the case tends
to be a little bit more casual so I'm
actually going to move over here because
I'm running out of real estate okay so
I've just taken some time to put
together a few quick ideas and basically
I'll just walk you through what I am
thinking the first thing I put was
competitive pricing now why did I put
this well pricing is one of the most
effective strategies when it comes to
capturing market share and if we're only
thinking about about capturing as much
market share as possible one of the most
direct ways that the company can try and
capture more customers is by lowering
their prices to a very competitive price
point now there's a whole set of
considerations that go into doing this
because you don't want to completely
obliterate your profit margins by
lowering the price too much but that is
one lever that the company has at its
disposal the second thing is robust
distribution now the reason I bring this
up is because distribution especially
when we're talking about cpg consumer
package Goods companies is extremely
extremely important because if you
aren't able to get your products into
stores where your customers are then how
are you going to maximize your chances
of making a sale and so making sure that
their distribution channels are set up
properly so that they don't have any
kind of bottlenecks whether it be like
at the bottling facility or with how
many Trucking shipments they can
accomplish or even like how many of the
inputs needed for the drink they can get
in their factories these are really
important things to consider to make
sure that you are able to properly meet
demand and not have a supply constraint
now finally I've put sales and marketing
campaigns and I think this is a little
bit self-explanatory but again sales and
marketing is super important when we are
launching a new product we need to get
the word out there that we are launching
this new product and we need to properly
build awareness in the consumer's mind
about this product so that they actually
get off the couch and go and buy the
product or if they're walking through a
convenience store for example they see
this produ in the shelves and they're
and they think to themselves oh hey I've
seen this somewhere let me try it and so
basically these three things I think are
critically important to consider now are
these the only three things that you
should consider when thinking about can
we capture 12.5% market share absolutely
not you can come up with a much bigger
list than I did but in the context of a
case I would try to come up with at
least three good solid reasons that you
can then discuss with your interviewer
now this brings us to the end of the
case which is simply the recommendation
and synthesis synthesis is just a fancy
word for summing up everything that
you've learned today and bundling it up
into a nice concise presentable answer
and so the typical way that this is
asked in case interviews is the
interviewer will say awesome so the CEO
of the company is now walking down the
hall to the conference room where you
and your team are posted up and you have
about 30 seconds before she walks in and
she's going to ask for an update what
would you tell her based on what you've
learned today and so the way you always
want to go about this is I would
recommend taking like 30 seconds okay
don't just dive right into it and just
take a second to look over everything
that you've learned today okay and think
through what the key insights are and
what they mean in terms of the product
strategy and whether or not they should
launch this product and then come up
with a few bullet points and the
structure that you generally want to
follow is you want to first start with
either restating the context and make
this super quick because you don't need
to belabor the point here they already
the CEO already know knows what's going
on at the company but you might want to
restate it quickly and then you want to
give your recommendation this is the
meat of it you want to follow up with
some potential risks and then you want
to end with some next steps and so
broadly speaking this structure works
pretty well I had a few people comment
on one of my past videos asking whether
or not restating the context was
necessary I would say no it's not
necessary although I personally do
appreciate restating the context just
because it helps to ground yourself
before you give the recommendation and I
think as long as you are keeping it very
brief like literally 10 seconds or less
then there's no problem with restating
the context and so basically an example
of how I would give this recommendation
and synthesize what I've learned from
this case today is I would say something
along the lines of awesome thanks so
much for joining us as a reminder we've
been working through the considerations
for the product strategy for electrolyte
and our recommendation at this moment is
to proceed with the launch but also to
give heavy consideration to how we go
about the launch because we've found
through our analysis that we need to
capture about 12.5% market share in
order to break even and and some levers
that we've thought about to achieve this
12.5% market share are ensuring that our
pricing is competitive making sure that
our distribution channels are robust and
able to meet demand and finally just
dialing in our sales and marketing
campaigns so that we are targeting the
right customers where they are now
despite our optimistic Outlook there are
obviously some risks as well including
the fact that our product launch
strategy may not succeed as much as we
anticipated due to the strength of our
competitors or perhaps our inability to
execute effectively on our distribution
but as a next step I would recommend
potentially doing some further research
into what our competition is currently
doing and also understanding a little
bit better what the potential demand for
this new product will be so that our
supply chain is prepared when the launch
comes okay so I hope that this video is
helpful and if you are currently working
on your case interview prep and you've
looked through a lot of different
resources and maybe you're still stuck
you might want to also consider some
one-on-one coaching with me as well
where I can walk you through the case
and pinpoint exactly the areas that you
can improve on if that sounds
interesting to you then make sure to
check out the link in the description
below but otherwise thanks so much for
being here I'll see you guys in the next
one peace